Daniel Barbara what a delight to be with
you and that was just such a I couldn't
imagine a more perfect opening thank you
so much thank you yeah awesome what you
were really doing was framing for us
where we are in this moment and of
course in the next session one of the
questions we're gonna address is where
are you and to where are you in history
we have to locate ourselves as you
pointed us so beautifully towards where
we are at this particular moment which
is unlike any other moment that ever was
and just like there's and we'll talk
more about a unique self of a person
there's a unique self of time a Yank
moment in time and perhaps we could
think about that kind of deep frame you
laid down for us in terms of what we
might want to call the first shock and
the second shock of existence so the
first shock of existence is as you
described you know Homo erectus emerges
you know dawn man dawn woman yeah you
know emerge right and all of a sudden
their surplus there's farming we've
moved past the first stage of
hunter-gatherers right who actually
gathered their food you know and live
and kind of with no sense of broader
time we moved there to kind of early
farming you know what they call a
horticultural where they're using you
know primitive farming instruments and
and by the way for everybody listening
i'm trancing horticultural because i
heard it for years and no one would
translate it I was so embarrassed to ask
what it meant so hard across this means
early farming instruments it's an easy
one right so there's early farming
instruments that all of a sudden there's
surplus time and because there's surplus
time we're not just thinking about how
to avoid the tiger we realized oh here I
am right into this new very strong self
reflective consciousness emerges much
stronger and then there's a first shock
of existence I'm gonna die the skull
grins at the banquet death steps in and
so the first shock of existence is the
realization that I'm going to die and as
Ernest Becker reminded us so many years
ago in his book the denial of death so
much of culture is to try and either
deny death or to possibly give dig
to life an entire cultural project with
enormous beauty and enormous distortion
and pain right emerges in response to
this first shock of existence this
realization that were self reflective
beings in time and we don't just need to
get through the next 15 minutes of
surviving the tiger
so the first shock of existence in some
sense produces culture produces all the
levels of consciousness that unfold that
you describe so gorgeously and then
really what you showed us was that all
of that beautiful emergence with all of
its progress and all of its unfolding at
the same time unconsciously brought us
to the second shock of existence and the
second shock of existence is when death
threatens not just the individual human
being but death threatens humanity right
the skull grins at the bank of once
again the second shock of existence we
brought ourselves to a place where
despite all of our advance in evolution
we might not survive unless we actually
become the future human so in some sense
it feels like what we're here to do is
is to respond together you know in our
evolutionary family to the second shock
of existence because the only possible
response to the second shock of
existence is a transformation of
identity right the lure of becoming in
which we actually become the future
human I think that's right yeah I think
that's right in crisis precedes
transformation right on it now right but
this is our crisis the exact degree
needed for transformation or devolution
and death the exact degree which is
which is the kindness of the universe
the love and the universe it's the
precise degree needed so if you if you
include the intention of creation always
going to higher order more complexity
out of crises out of chaos Nature has
designed a way to take a jump to greater
order and we are the first ones to be
conscious but that's what's happening to
us right and that that's our beautiful
that's our response to the second shock
of existence and Barbara and you kind of
articulated what we might call the
Goldilocks principle right which is just
right not too hot not too cold that's
just the right amount which is the love
principle
universe to force us to transform
without destroying us so it's always an
invitation it's just perfect and I've
coined this phrase it's a conscious
evolution conscious of evolutions been
going on for billions of years but we're
the first generation to be conscious of
evolution conscious we're affecting
evolution and in some sense conscious we
are evolution yeah we are evolution is
self-aware I mean it was a huge thing if
you think of the genius of evolution for
those billions of years and we are that
becoming self-aware well we are that
that's the future human we are that that
is the future human you know Barbara
what you shared that I thought was so
beautiful that's the essence of what
you've been teaching for a long time is
you shared a new narrative a new
universe story that actually has purpose
and meaning in it that is scientifically
integrated and literate that gives us a
place where we're at humanity and us as
individuals in the whole universe
narrative and so you told the evolution
story right the science evolution story
which is the things progress towards
more and more complexity but that what
we understand in science that is systems
evolve towards more ordered complexity
on the exterior they also have deeper
interior which is deeper consciousness
and that that is a prima facie purpose
of universe right that it's experiencing
itself more and more deeply to every
animal with a what does that work from a
fascia mean tell us come on whether
whether that purpose was intended by a
Great Creator beforehand or it's
emergent doesn't really matter it's
happening that's right it's happening I
mean there it is it's happening it's
self-evident yeah exactly it's
self-evident is a very good phrase for
it and so as we're getting more and more
complex biology and more complex nervous
systems that are going from reptilian
mammalian primate to with neocortex
abstraction in the capacity for an
abstract self then we get a being that
has the capacity to be not just in the
moment but also outside of the moment
this is kind of the power of other than
now that can be very painful but also
uniquely beautiful or we can see how
things change over time and there's
direction to that change which is
evolution we can actually get evolution
consciously and then we can get volition
and choice consciously and we can become
conscious agents for the evolutionary
impulse in the universe so in a very
real way we are the universe that the
impulse that's evolving everything that
ever has been or ever will be woke up to
itself yeah as an agent for that yeah
and that we have a massive impact on the
world we aren't just in the environment
we're creating the environment and as
you said all biology does that right
from from the early creatures coming out
of the ocean changing the atmosphere but
we with our with the power of our
technology do it so powerfully that
we're at a point right now where we're
called to take a deeper degree of
responsibility not just for our lives
but for our impact on the whole it's so
true and from Martin it's a spiritual
point of view it looks to me like that
process is the intention of the process
itself to create more conscious yes and
that therefore the process has divine
intent or goodness because when I was
growing up there was a materialistic
view that the universe was meaningless
it had no direction it wasn't going
anywhere and it was random error and
physical laws but we're saying something
very deep it doesn't yet have a good
languaging for it we know the language
of God of spirit but what is the
language for the impulse of evolution
having intention toward higher
consciousness greater freedom more
complex order that the future human is
is I'm looking for that word in that
languaging that we're looking for we're
gonna unfold together right as we kind
of move through these series and you
know friends really what we're saying is
the universe isn't a fact it's a story
and we're the stars of the story but not
as a slogan as Barbara's so beautifully
unfolded in Daniel grounded but actually
has the best take of the leading edge of
all the integrated fields of knowledge
today so be with this next session as we
take the next step into how this impacts
and transforms our lives in the most
immediate and clear way thank you